<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints great duty in time of the dangerous afflictions, persecutions, and oppressions, they may meet with in the troublesome and tempestuous sea of this world, either by spiritual or temporal enemies. Preached in a farewel-sermon by Mr. George Thorne, of Weymouth in Dorset-shire. From Psal. 37. 34. Wait on the Lord, and keep his way. Published by a friend.</title>
            <author>Thorne, George, of Weymouth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1057B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220883</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832268</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62465)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2138:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints great duty in time of the dangerous afflictions, persecutions, and oppressions, they may meet with in the troublesome and tempestuous sea of this world, either by spiritual or temporal enemies. Preached in a farewel-sermon by Mr. George Thorne, of Weymouth in Dorset-shire. From Psal. 37. 34. Wait on the Lord, and keep his way. Published by a friend.</title>
                  <author>Thorne, George, of Weymouth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The saints duty in time of danger.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXVII, 34 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36740:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS Great DUTY IN Time of the dangerous Afflictions, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, and Oppreſſions, they may meet with in the troubleſome and tempeſtuous Sea of this World, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſpiritual or temporal Enemies.</p>
            <p>Preached in a FAREWEL-SERMON BY Mr. <hi>GEORGE THORNE,</hi> of <hi>Weymouth</hi> in <hi>Dorſet-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>From <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.34.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wait on the Lord, and keep his Way.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by a Friend.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EXOD. 14.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And Moſes ſaid to the people, Fear ye not; ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year 1664</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36740:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36740:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:36740:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36740:3"/>
            <head>The SAINTS GREAT DUTY IN Time of Affliction, Perſecution, and Oppreſſion.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 37.34.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Wait on the Lord, and keep his Way.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>NOt knowing whether ever I ſhall ſpeak to you more from this place, being willing to leave a word in ſeaſon, I ſhall recommend to you what in anſwer to prayer I have received of the Lord for the directing me in my courſe in this gloomy dark day; being well aſſured that as many of us as walk by this Rule, and ſail by this Compaſs (however we may be ſcattered by the tempeſtuous ſtorms we meet with here in the Sea of this World) ſhall ſhortly arrive at, and meet in our deſired Port, the Haven of eternal Reſt and Happineſs: What therefore the Lord hath ſaid to me, and that with a ſtrong hand, that ſay I unto you in the Name of the Lord; <hi>Wait on the Lord, and keep his Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſcope of this Pſalm, is to direct the people of God, and to encourage them to keep on in the courſe of godlineſs at ſuch times, as when the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>proſper, flouriſh,</hi> and <hi>grow great,</hi> and the Godly fro <hi>afflicted, troubled, perſecuted,</hi> and <hi>oppreſſed:</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36740:4"/> And there are two general parts of the Pſalm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixtly ſpoken unto throughout. The one is for Direction; the other for Encouragement. The Text appertains to the former part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the ſum of the Directions may be reduced unto two Heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they take heed of ſuch inward Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions and perturbations of ſpirit, as through the remainder of corruption they are ſubject unto; and by the temptations of Satan, and the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of wicked men, they will be put upon through this occaſion: More particularly he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warns them to take heed of <hi>Envy, verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7. and of <hi>Anger, verſ.</hi> 8. And what need there is at ſuch a time to watch againſt the exorbitant workings of theſe Paſſions, none that obſerve their own hearts, can well be ignorant; ſuch being the unworthy, inſolent, and provoking Carriage of the wicked toward the poor People of God, as is able, as we may ſay, to move a Saint. Hence that of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.23. <hi>But as for me, my feet were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well-nigh ſlipt; for I was envious at the fooliſh, when I ſaw the proſperity of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Attend therefore to the counſel of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Fret not thy ſelf becauſe of evil-doers, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be thou envious againſt the workers of iniquity. Fret not thy ſelf becauſe of him that proſpereth in his way, becauſe of the man that bringeth wicked devices to paſs: Ceaſe from anger, and forſake wrath. Fret not thy-ſelfe in any wiſe to doe evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36740:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That they ſo carry themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Lord in keeping on in their way of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him, as becomes thoſe that firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and ſtedfaſtly hope in him for his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>There are many particular directions to this purpoſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Truſt in the Lord, and do good. Verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Delight thy ſelf alſo in the Lord. Verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord. Verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Reſt in the Lord, and wait patiently for him. Verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Depart from evil, and do good;</hi> and here in the Text, <hi>Wait on the Lord and keep his way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words contain Advice and Counſel for the people of God, and 'tis conſiderable, either with reſpect to the troubles and temptations of the people of God in general; or with reſpect to that particular that is immediately touched on before the Text, <hi>verſ.</hi> 33. <hi>The wicked watcheth the righteous, and ſeeketh to ſlay him.</hi> Upon this ſomthing is ſpoken by way of encouragement to the righteous, <hi>verſ.</hi> 33. <hi>The Lord will not leave him in his hand, nor condemn him when he is judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Though he may let him fall into the hands of the VVicked, he will not leave him there; though the VVicked may fit in judgment on him, and paſs ſentence againſt him, yet the Lord will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him; yea, when he is judged he is chaſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Lord, that he ſhould not be condemned with the VVorld. Thus for the encouragement of the Righteous.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36740:5"/>2. There is ſomthing by way of direction in the words read: <hi>Wait on the Lord, and keep his Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the words, conſidered under this double reference, we have this profitable point of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>However it go with the truly Godly here in this World, more eſpecially when the wicked watch the Righteous to do them a miſchief, it is their beſt way to wait on the Lord, and keep his Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſpend time to ſhew you who are truly Godly, and who are VVicked. It is ſaid of the Godly man, <hi>verſ.</hi> 31. <hi>The Law of God is in his heart.</hi> Such then as from the Law of God in their hearts have reſpect to all his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, walking in all the Statutes, and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God blameleſs, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. ſuch are truly godly: And ſuch as from the Dominion of ſin in them, are evil Doers, workers of iniquity, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to the Luſts of the Fleſh, and of the mind, according to the courſe of this World, of the Prince of the Power of the Air, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they are wicked.</p>
            <p>In the handling of this Point, according to my wonted method, I ſhall ſpeak firſt to what is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and then to what is expreſly laid down.</p>
            <p>Here are two things ſuppoſed in this point; the one more General, the other more Particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, In General;</hi> 'Tis ſuppoſed, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the truly Godly may be full of Troubles, Afflictions and Diſtreſſes in this VVorld; for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36740:5"/> when 'tis ſaid, <hi>However it go with the truly Godly;</hi> the meaning is, how evilly, how badly ſoever, though they be never ſo much troubled, afflicted, and diſtreſſed; wherein 'tis ſuppoſed that it may go very ill, that the truly Godly may be full of troubles, ſufferings, and diſtreſſes: this is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plainly held forth in Scripture, in ſuch Texts as theſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.19. <hi>John</hi> 16.33. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22. but ſo ſadly experienced in all Ages, that we need not ſpend time in the clearing of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, More Particularly;</hi> It is ſuppoſed, <hi>That 'tis the manner and guiſe of the Wicked, to watch the Righteous to miſchief them:</hi> ſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 32, and <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>The Wicked plotteth againſt the juſt;</hi> (or as the Margent, <hi>practiſeth) i. e.</hi> his wit, and skill, his labour and Judgment is employed againſt him: And <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>The wicked have drawn their Sword, and bent their Bow, to caſt down the poor and the needy, and to ſlay ſuch as be of upright con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.2. the Pſalmiſt prayes, <hi>Hide me from the ſecret Counſel of the Wicked; from the Inſurrection of the Workers of Iniquity; who whet their tongues like a Sword, and bend their Bowes to ſhoot their Arrows, even bitter words, that they may ſhoot ſecret in at the perfect: ſuddenly do they ſhoot at him, and fear not.</hi> So we read in that <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.20, 21. of thoſe <hi>that watch for iniquity, that make a man an offendour for a word, that lay a ſnare for him that reproveth in the Gate, and that turn aſide the Juſt for a thing of nought.</hi> Thus it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36740:6"/> hath been ever ſince the beginning. So wicked <hi>Cain</hi> watcheth righteous <hi>Abel</hi> to kill him, Gen. 4.8. <hi>And Cain talked with Abel his Brother; and it came to paſſe that when they were in the field, that Cain roſe up againſt his Brother Abel, and ſlew him:</hi> And thus have <hi>Cain</hi>'s brood done all down along (for he was of the wicked one, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12.) So hath <hi>Eſau</hi> watched righteous <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 27.41, 42. comforting himſelf, that he ſhould have ſhortly a time to do him the miſchief that he intended him. So <hi>Saul</hi> watcheth righteous <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 19.11. <hi>Saul ſent Meſſengers to Davids houſe, to watch him, and ſlay him in the Morning:</hi> And ſo did others, his wicked adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, watch him, as you have him complaining, Pſal. 38.12. <hi>They that ſeek after my life, lay Snares for me; and they that ſeek my hurt, ſpeak miſchievous things, and imagine deceit all the day long:</hi> And Pſal. 140.5. <hi>The proud have laid a Snare for me, and Cords; they have ſpread a Net by the way ſide; they have ſet Grins for me.</hi> So did <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> Familiars, as he calls them, Jer. 20.10. <hi>For I heard the defaming of many, fear on every ſide: Report ſay they, and we will report it: All my Familiars</hi> (or as in the Margent, every man of my peace) <hi>watched for my halting; ſaying, perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture he will be enticed, &amp; we ſhall prevail againſt him, and we ſhall take our revenge of him:</hi> While they pretended friendſhip and peace, they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nothi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but miſchief, even the taking of their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36740:6"/> revenge on him. So the Preſidents and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, watched righteous <hi>Daniel</hi> to miſchief him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.4. where firſt they ſeek to find occaſion againſt him, concerning the Kingdom; they would gladly have ſound any occaſion againſt him, to have accuſed him of Diſloyalty, Sedition, Treaſon, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, or at leaſt Falſhood and Unfaithfulneſs; but here they could find no fault, his very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies being Judges, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. In the next place, therefore they plot, to find occaſion againſt him from the <hi>Law</hi> of his <hi>God;</hi> and therefore enticing the King to make a Law againſt the Law of <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> God, they quickly catch him. So you may ſee the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> watched the Lord Jeſus, that <hi>Juſt One,</hi> Luke 6.7. <hi>And the Scribes and Phariſees watched Him, whether He would heal on the Sabbath Day, that they might find an accuſation againſt Him.</hi> It ſeems they had a Law againſt doing good on the Sabbath Day: So, Luke 20.19, 20. <hi>And the chief Prieſts, and the Scribes, ſought to lay hands on Him, and they feared the people; for they perceived that he had ſpoken this Parable againſt them; and they watched Him, and ſent forth ſpies, which ſhould feign themſelves juſt men, that they might take hold of his words, that ſo they might deliver Him to the Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Governour:</hi> They endeavour to <hi>trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan</hi> Him, that they might give him over to the ſecular Power. Time would fail to ſhew how they watched the Apoſtles, &amp; the Saints, all down
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36740:7"/> along throughout all ages: Neither need we ſearch the records of former ages, in this matter, for evidence, our own times affording pregnant proof, more than enough in this thing; and as it hath been, and now is, ſo it will be to the end of this wicked world, the guiſe and manner of the wicked, thus to watch the Righteous to do him a miſchief.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that there is the ſame principle of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and enmity, in the Wicked againſt the Righteous now, as ever, yea, and ever will to the worlds end: That enmity that we read of in <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. is a laſting enmity, as long as there are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Seed of the Serpent in the world, it will work; It is an enmity in nature, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.27. <hi>He that is upright in the way, is an abomination to the Wicked;</hi> and the wicked muſt ceaſe to be wicked, ere this will ceaſe to be. As there are ſome Creatures that have an enmity in nature, as the Wolf, and the Sheep, ſo that enmity is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated to all of the kind that partake of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: So is the Enmity that the Children of the Wicked one have againſt the Children of God; As therefore the Wolf need not to be taught to watch to devour the Sheep, it being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to him: So the Wicked need not be taught to do the Saints a miſchief, having a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple within them inclining, and inſtructing them thereunto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is the ſame neceſſary ground and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36740:7"/> of their hatred of them: Though there be no juſt ground of the wickeds hatred of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous (hence <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of their hating him without a cauſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.4. that is, without juſt cauſe on his part) yet there is a neceſſary ground of their hatred, and that continueth now as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and will continue as long as there are any <hi>truly Godly;</hi> and what that is, you may ſee in that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.20. <hi>They alſo that render evil for good, are mine adverſaries; becauſe I follow the thing that good is.</hi> The true ground and reaſon of their being adverſaries unto <hi>David,</hi> was this, Becauſe he followed that which they hated.</p>
            <p>Thus our Saviour ſhewing his Diſciples how they ſhould be hated of the World, acquaints them with the true cauſe and ground of the Worlds hatred, <hi>John</hi> 15.19. <hi>If you were of the World, the world would love its own; but becauſe you are not of the World, but I have choſen you out of the world, therefore the World hateth you.</hi> And that this is the proper ground of the Worlds hatred, is moſt manifeſt, for that the ſame perſon, whom the world loved while he was of the world; when called out of the world into the Kingdom of Chriſt, then is he hated of thoſe that before loved him; as in <hi>Paul.</hi> And if a perſon that profeſſeth himſelf the Diſciple of Chriſt, and is hated of the world, ſhall forſake the aſſembly of Saints, and turn back from the way of righteouſneſſe, and run into the ſame exceſſe of riot with the prophane
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36740:8"/> world, none more worlds darling than he. So that it is Godlineſs, Holineſs, and true Religion, that is the true ground of the worlds hatred. So 1. <hi>John</hi> 3.12. <hi>Not as Cain who was of the wicked one and ſlew his brother: and wherefore ſlew he him? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his own works were evil, and his brothers righteous.</hi> This was the true cauſe of his hatred; and while that the cauſe remaineth, while godly Men continue to walk in the wayes of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the wicked will continue to hate them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Devil, whoſe Children theſe wicked ones are, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8, 10. is ſtill as malicious, and induſtrious as ever, to put them upon this. We read of Satan in that, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. that he goeth up and down like a roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour; and as far as the Lord permits him, he acts wicked men in whom he ruleth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. to do what miſchief they can to the Godly; yea, and in the laſt times he is ſo far from abat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his rage, as that we read, <hi>his wrath groweth the hotter, becauſe he knoweth he hath but a ſhort time,</hi> Rev. 12.12.</p>
            <p>While therefore the principle of enmity, which is in the wicked againſt the Saints, remaineth, and while the ground of their hatred continues, and Satan is as induſtriouſly ſtirring them up as ever, nought elſe can be expected, but that they watch the righteous to do them a miſchief.</p>
            <p>But now, wher ſhall the righteous do? ſhall he render evil for evil, and watch the wicked that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36740:8"/> he may miſchieve them? God forbid; what ſhall he forſake his righteouſneſſe, and leave off to be godly? no, in no wiſe. But if ye would know, O ye Saints and righteous Ones, what to do in this caſe, I am ſent of God at this time to inſtruct you, <hi>That it will be your beſt way to wait on she Lord, and keep his way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I come to what is expreſly aſſerted in the point, <hi>That however it go with the truly Godly here in this World,</hi> more eſpecially when the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked watcheth the righteous to miſchieve them, <hi>'tis their beſt way to wait on the Lord, and keepe his way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I ſhall ſpeak by way of Explication, in ſhewing, 1. What it is to wait on the Lord. 2. What it is to keep his way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To wait on the Lord, is taken more larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or more ſtrictly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>More largly.</hi> And ſo it is the ſame with ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord, attending and following the Lord, and takes in the whole duty of the Saints; wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Lord as a Souldier on his Captain, or as a Servant on his Maſter: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.2. <hi>Behold! as the eyes of the Servants look to the hands of their Maſters, and as the eyes of a Maiden unto the hand of her Miſtris; ſo our eyes wait on the Lord our God.</hi> So in that, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Turn thou to thy God, and keep Mercy and Judgement, and wait on thy God continually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>More ſtrictly,</hi> And ſo it intends a patient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36740:9"/> the Lords Salvation. 'Tis the continued exerciſe of Faith and Hope; it is Faith and Hope eekt out: So here <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Reſt on the Lord; wait patiently.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. when he cries out of the depths, as he ſayes <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. then <hi>Verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>I Wait for the Lord, my ſoul doth wait; and in his word do I hope. My ſoul waiteth for the Lord, more than they that watch for the morning, I ſay, more than they that watch for the morning.</hi> We have both theſe together in that, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.25, 26. <hi>The Lord is good to them that wait for him; to the ſoul that ſeeketh him.</hi> There it is taken as largly as ſeeking after God: but it follows, <hi>It is good that a man ſhould both hope and quietly wait for the Salvation of the Lord:</hi> there it is taken for the continued exerciſe of hope; for a patient expectation of the Lord's Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What it is to keep the Way of the Lord: here mind, The way of the Lord may be underſtood, of that way wherein he walketh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his People, which is aptly ſtil'd, the way of his Providence; or, of that way wherein he requires his People to walk towards him, and is properly ſtiled, the way of his Precepts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>There is the Way of Gods Providence,</hi> in which he walketh towards us: of which, that <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.30. ſpeaketh; <hi>As for God, his Way is perfect.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.10. <hi>All the Paths or Wayes of the Lord, are Mercy and Truth unto ſuch as keep his Covenant, and Teſtimonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:36740:9"/>
            <p>Now, if it be thus taken here, Then to keepe his Way, is diligently to attend his Hand, and to obſerve his Carriage, and ordering, in all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls his People, more eſpecially in all that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that comes on them: For whatever trouble comes upon the People of God, and whoever be the inſtruments of inflicting, the Lord hath his way in it, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.9. ordering it, as to the kind, as to the meaſure, as to the ſeaſon, as to the continuance, as to the ends and fruits.</p>
            <p>Now, to obſerve the Lord's Hand, and to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Way, in ordering his Providences, and our troubles, this is to keep his Way. So <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.8. <hi>In the way of thy Judgements we have waited for thee:</hi> as if he had ſaid, <hi>We have waited on the Lord, and kept his Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>There is the way of God's Precepts;</hi> in which he commandeth his People to walk: And thus is this phraſe moſt commonly taken. So 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.22. where 'tis ſaid of <hi>Amon, He forſook the Lord God of his Fathers, and walked not in the Way of the Lord;</hi> i.e. <hi>not in the Way of his Commandements.</hi> Thus <hi>David</hi> ſpake of the way of his Precepts, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.27. <hi>Make me underſtand the way of thy Precepts:</hi> And if it be taken thus, then to keep the Way of the Lord, is to walk in his Statutes, and to obſerve his Commandments to do them. So <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. The Lord teſtifies of <hi>Abraham; I know him, that he will command his Children and his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the Way
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36740:10"/> of the Lord, to do Juſtice and Judgement.</hi> So in <hi>Job</hi> 23.11, 12. <hi>My feet have held his ſteps, his way have I kept and not declined: neither have I gone back from the Commandments of his lips:</hi> So to walk in his Wayes, and to keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, are the ſame, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.1, 2.</p>
            <p>So that the ſum of all, is, However it be with the truly Godly, more eſpecially when the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed do watch them to do them a miſchief, their beſt way is, to attend on the Lord, to follow him, to walk on in the ways of his Commandements; ſo eying the hand of the Lord in all that befalls them, as they that patiently expect, and quietly wait for the Salvation of the Lord. Thus for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</p>
            <p>I now come to the Demonſtration, which ſhall be diſpatcht by clearing, That it is the honeſteſt, the wiſeſt, the ſafeſt, the moſt comfortable, and moſt honourable Way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> This is the moſt innocent, juſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Way; yea truly, this is the only good, honeſt, and right Way.</p>
            <p>I am to ſhew what is the beſt for a Godly man, to whom no way is good, but what is juſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. There are indeed other ways which a man may take when he is in trouble through the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eds watching him to do him a miſchief, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to eſcape the miſchief intended him; but they are not juſt and honeſt. I ſhall inſtance in theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:36740:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>1. By ſinful complying with the wicked in their ungodly ways, thereby to abate the edge of their wrath: This was the way <hi>Peter</hi> took, when in the High Prieſts Hall, he not only denyes his Maſter-but backs his denyal with an Oath; yea, being a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong a curſing crew, that ſhould ſeem would not believe him elſe, he falls a curſing and ſwearing that he knew not the man, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.74.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By ſinful ſhifting or ſhuffling, through Lyes or deceitful Equivocations, to avoid the miſchief intended: This was the way that <hi>Abraham</hi> took to eſcape the miſchief, that he thought at one time the Men of <hi>Gerar</hi> might do to him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. and that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> might do to him at another time for his wives ſake; wherein, though <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did not tell a down-right untruth, as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth the matter to <hi>Abimilech,</hi> yet he did ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſhuffle in making uſe of a deceitful Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for his ſafety.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By angrily and revengfully rendring Evil for Evil, thereby thinking to pay the wicked in his own Coyn, and to avenge a mans own quarrel. This was the courſe that <hi>David</hi> was about to take againſt <hi>Nabal,</hi> had he not been prevented by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigaeles</hi> wiſdom, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.33.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By baſely deſerting the Place that the Lord hath put a man in, and requires him to abide in. This was that which <hi>Shemaiah</hi> would have out <hi>Nehemiah</hi> upon but he refuſed to hearken to him, in <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.10.11. not but that a man may forſake
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36740:11"/> his place, not only of habitation, but alſo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> publick ſtation and employment, in ſome caſes when that the Lord calls him off; but this is no baſe deſerting; Baſe deſerting is, when out of cowardlineſs and baſe fear, a man withdraws him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from his place, in which, and at that time, when the Lord requires him to abide, that he may provide for his own ſafety: This was the way <hi>Moſes</hi> would have taken, when the Lord was ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to deliver his People, had the Lord left him to himſelf, as you may ſee at laſt in the 3d. and 4th <hi>Chapters</hi> of the Book of <hi>Exodu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. By rebelliouſly and traiterouſly stepping out of the place that God hath ſet a man in. This was that way they tempted <hi>David</hi> unto, in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4. and which <hi>Abiſhai</hi> would have taken, had not <hi>David</hi> hindered him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. Now none of theſe ways are juſt and honeſt, being all of them contrary to the Command, and a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from God to the Creature, as I ſhall clear particularly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That ſinfully to comply with the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to abate the edge of their wrath, is contrary to the Command, is clear from theſe Scriptures, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Be ye not therefore partakers with them;</hi> that is, with the Wicked, with the Children of diſobedience: Now one way of partaking with them, is, by ſinful compliance: hence <hi>verſ.</hi> 11 <hi>Have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works o darkneſs;</hi> have you no hand, do not you bear a part
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36740:11"/> be not drawn in to comply in theſe things: To this purpoſe is that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Be not conformed to this World. Nonconformity</hi> to this World, is a Chriſtians duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That ſinfully to ſhift and ſhuffle through Lyes and deceitful Equivocations to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for ones ſafety, is contrary to the Command of God, clear is that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.9. where <hi>Abimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi> reproving <hi>Abraham</hi> for his practice, tells him, <hi>Thou haſt done things to me that ought not to be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That to render evil for evil, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge our ſelves, is againſt the Command of God; clear is that, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.21. <hi>Say not thou, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence evil, but wait on the Lord, and he ſhall ſave thee.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.15. <hi>See that none render evil for evil to any man.</hi> Rom. 12.17. <hi>Recompence to no man evil for evil:</hi> and 19. <hi>Dearly beloved avenge not your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That baſely to deſert the place that God hath put a man in, is againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God; clear is that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.24. <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, let every one wherein he is called, therein abide with God;</hi> and as in the condition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſo in the place whereunto, till God remove him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That rebelliouſly to ſtep out of a mans place, is againſt the Command of God, is clear from, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.4. <hi>If the ſpirit of thy Ruler riſe up againſt thee, leave not thy place; for yielding pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36740:12"/> great offences.</hi> Subjects are here directed how to carry themſelves when that the ſpirit of the Ruler riſes up againſt them; the counſel that the Spirit here gives, is, <hi>That they keep their place,</hi> not in a way of rebellious oppoſition, but in way of yielding ſubjection; leave not thy place as a ſubject, contain thy ſelf within the bounds of thine own calling and condition, bridling all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal paſſions, and forbearing all unlawful at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, to ward off the wrath of the Ruler; he ſpeaketh not againſt a prudent withdrawing from a ſtorm, as <hi>David</hi> from <hi>Saul, Elias</hi> from <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> from <hi>Herod,</hi> but againſt a diſloyal and rebellious defection; as <hi>Iſrael</hi> to their <hi>Tents,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.16. So that whatever the provocations be that the Rulers give, Subjects muſt ſubmit themſelves, by yielding active obedience in all things which they command according to God, and by patiently enduring what they inflict on us, though for righteouſneſs ſake; keeping our ſelves in the ſome humble, obedient, and loyal temper, whatever provocations we meet with to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And that in all theſe wayes there is a departing from God to the Creature, ariſing from a diſtruſt of his All-ſufficiency to provide for us in his way, and from a conceit of our own wiſdom to provide better for our ſafety, is moſt manifeſt; therefore theſe ways being contrary to the Command of God, and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urious to his All-ſufficiency, are not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36740:12"/> juſt and honeſt; <hi>but to wait on the Lord, and to keep his way,</hi> this is the good, the right, and the honeſt Way. See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23, where he tels them, that he will ſhew them <hi>the good and the right way;</hi> and what that is, he acquaints them in the next verſe, <hi>Only fear the Lord, and ſerve him in Truth, with all your heart,</hi> which is to the ſame purpoſe, with <hi>wait on the Lord, and keep his way;</hi> that is, the honeſt, and good Way, in which the Lord commandeth his People to walk, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.27. His Commandments being <hi>holy, juſt,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> Rom. 7.12. The way of his Commandments muſt needs be <hi>good, juſt,</hi> and <hi>honeſt;</hi> yea, and his Commandments being the Rule; the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of a way lyes in its conformity thereunto; and this is the way that is agreeable to the Command of God, as in the Text.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is the wiſeſt Way: When a man hath many wiſe, ſubtile, and powerful enemies watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to miſchieve him, he had need behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wiſely. Hence when our Saviour ſends forth his Diſciples as Sheep among Wolves, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16. he ſayes to them, <hi>Be wiſe as Serpents, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent as Doves,</hi> he adviſeth them to look to the wiſeſt, as well as the honeſteſt way. Now howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver carnal men do think ſome one of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned wayes to be the wiſeſt, yet it will be apparent, that <hi>to wait on the Lord, and keep his Way,</hi> is the wiſeſt courſe; by theſe two ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36740:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is the way which the trueſt and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt VViſdom, the VViſdom of God, doth direct unto; So here in the Text. So in that <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.14. he complains of his enemies, and of falſe witneſſes that were riſen up againſt him, that did breath out cruelty, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. and then by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit he commends to himſelf and others, ſuitable advice in ſuch a caſe; <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Wait on the Lord.</hi> So <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. there <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Hoſts are at the heels of the poor <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> &amp; he counts of nothing but of deſtroying them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.9. and they for their parts knew not how to eſcape: Now ſayes <hi>Moſes</hi> to them, <hi>Fear ye not, ſtand ſtill, and ſee the Salvation of the Lord.</hi> So that whatever diſtreſs the People of God are in, this is the way the VViſdom of God directs unto; for what the Word of God in the Scripture directs to, that the Wiſdom of God directs, as is clear from that, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.49.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is the way that the wiſeſt men have taken. <hi>David</hi> was a wiſe man; we read of him in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.30. that <hi>David</hi> behaved himſelfe more wiſely than all the Servants of <hi>Saul,</hi> ſo that his name was much ſet by: Now this was the way that he took, as you have him ſpeaking in that, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.21. <hi>I have kept the ways of the Lord, and have not wickedly departed from my God; for all thy Judgments were before me; and I did not put away his Statutes from me,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.110. <hi>The wicked have laid a ſnare for me, yet I erred not from thy Precepts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:36740:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> was a wiſe man; hence that Proverb, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.3. <hi>Wiſer than Daniel;</hi> and he took this courſe when that his Enemies had laid a ſnare for him to take away his life; <hi>yet</hi> (Dan. 6.10.) <hi>he declined not from the way of the Lord, but waited on the Lord, and kept his way, as aforetime;</hi> as you may there read.</p>
            <p>Yea, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Wiſdom of God, he took this courſe, as you may read, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. where when certain of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> came, ſaying to him, <hi>Get thee out, and depart hence, for Herod will kill thee, verſ.</hi> 31. He anſwered <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. <hi>Go ye and tell that Fox, Behold, I caſt out Devils, and do cures to day and to morrow;</hi> that is, I will do the work of my Father; I will follow what he hath ſent me about, and keep his <hi>Way,</hi> whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of me. Thus you ſee it is the wiſeſt way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is the ſafeſt way; when a man is beſet with the wicked that ſeek to miſchieve him, 'tis a time to look after the ſafeſt way; <hi>now to wait on the Lord, and to keep his Way,</hi> is the ſafeſt courſe a man can take: <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.9. <hi>He that walks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, walks ſurely.</hi> And 28. 18. <hi>Whoſo walketh uprightly, ſhall be ſaved.</hi> I know carnal wiſdom thinks otherwiſe, and mocks at this: But I am ſpeaking to the People of God, who are capable of receiving and underſtanding what I ſhall offer, and to them this will appear to be the ſafeſt way, by theſe two Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> This is the readieſt way for the People
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36740:14"/> of God to eſcape that miſchief which the wicked deviſe, and intend againſt them, <hi>Prov,</hi> 18.10. <hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower; the Righteous fly to it, and are ſafe:</hi> But how do they fly to this ſtrong hold, but upon the wings of Faith and Hope, whereby they wait on the Lord? and being fled for refuge to this ſtrong hold, they are ſale, and continue ſafe by abiding there, which is by keeping the Way of the Lord: Hence that, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.7. <hi>When a mans wayes pleaſe the Lord, he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him.</hi> Now for thoſe whoſe wayes pleaſe him, who wait on him, and keep his way, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth even their enemies to be at peace with them, theſe ſeveral wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sometimes by changing their hearts, and by making them even of Enemies, to become Friends. So we find he changed the heart of <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> that whereas his enmity was ſo enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the miſ-information of <hi>Haman,</hi> as that he had ſigned the Decree for the utter deſtroying of the People of God; yet afterwards he grants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Jews</hi> to gather themſelves together, and ſtand for their lives, to deſtroy, ſlay, and cauſe to periſh all the power of the people of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince that ſhould aſſault, both little ones, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and to take the ſpoil of them for a prey. So he changed the heart of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> with reſpect to the three Worthies, whom in the heat of his fury be commanded to be caſt into the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36740:14"/> 
               <hi>fiery Furnace,</hi> heated ſeven times hotter than aforetime; yet afterwards his heart is ſo turned towards them, as that he greatly promotes them in the Province of <hi>Babylon;</hi> as you may read <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. So the Lord changed the heart of <hi>Paul,</hi> who of a perſecuting <hi>Saul,</hi> became a preaching <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 1.23. abounding in love to Chriſt and his Members, as he did before in rage and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By reſtraining ſometimes their envy and fury; ſo that though their hearts continue as full of bitterneſs, malice and revenge, as formerly, yet he bindeth up their hands, ſo as that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not execute the miſchief they intend againſt his People. So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.5. <hi>The ſtout-hearted are ſpoiled,</hi> or diſarmed; <hi>they have ſlept their ſleep, and none of the men of might have found their hands.</hi> All which expreſſions tend to ſhew the reſtraint that is laid upon them; and by whom, you may ſee, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>At thy Rebuke, O God of Jacob, both the Chariots and the Horſes are caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a dead ſleep:</hi> Hence that, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Surely the wrath of men ſhall praiſe thee;</hi> that is, as much of it as he ſuffers for to break forth; <hi>for the remaind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of wrath wilt thou reſtrain.</hi> We have a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example of this in <hi>Laban, Gen.</hi> 31. who is not only rebuked by the Lord in his not purſuit after <hi>Jacob,</hi> with a charge not to hurt him, but is over-ruled to tell <hi>Jacob</hi> how the God of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpake to him, as you may read, <hi>verſ.</hi> 29.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36740:15"/> whatever be the fury and rage of the enemy, he can ſay unto it, <hi>Thus far ſhalt thou go, and no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> as Job 38.11.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He maketh their enemies to be at peace with them, ſometimes by enclining them to uſe his People well, and to treat them peaceably, after that they have them in their power and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their hand, <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.11. <hi>The Lord ſaid, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily it ſhall be well with thy remnant: verily, I will cauſe the enemy to treat thee well, in time of evil, and in the time of affliction.</hi> So we read, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.46. He made them to be pityed of all them that carryed them away captives.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Alwayes by over-ruling what they do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, ſo as that it ſhall not hurt them. So <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.17. <hi>No weapon that is formed againſt thee ſhall proſper.</hi> But of whom is this ſpoken? it follows there, <hi>This is the heritage of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord:</hi> It may proſper to put them to ſmart, but not to hurt them: As the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 18.10. <hi>I am with thee, and no man ſhall ſet on thee to hurt thee.</hi> So he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all his, in that <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10. So that the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt way to eſcape the miſchief that our enemies deſign againſt us, is, to <hi>wait on the Lord, and to keep his way,</hi> whatever carnal wiſdom thinks, or ſuggeſts to the contrary: It is true, this is the way to be hated, and to have many enemies, who from their malice and rage, will deviſe and deſign much miſchief againſt us: but <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31. <hi>If
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36740:15"/> God be for us, who ſhall be againſt us?</hi> that is, it matters not who they are that are againſt us. This then is the ſafeſt way; hence <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.31. <hi>Who ſo hearkeneth unto me, ſhall dwell ſafely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know this ſeems a Paradox to the men of the World, and they think ſome other wayes to be more ſafe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Some think that ſinful compliance is a ſafer way; but their errour will be manifeſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that duly conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That hereby they do more encourage the wicked World againſt them, whilſt they partly comply, but will not run into the ſame exceſs of riot with them. So <hi>Lots</hi> compliance with the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Sodomites</hi> in offering them his Daughters, did but encourage them the more againſt him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.9. <hi>And they ſaid, Stand back;</hi> which words may either refer unto <hi>Lot,</hi> and then they hold forth how they were enraged by his motion; or to one another, as contending who ſhould fall foul on him firſt: and this agreeth with the following words; <hi>And they ſaid again, This one fellow came in to ſojourn, and he will needs be a Judge: Now will we deal worſe with thee, than with them, and they preſſed ſore upon the man:</hi> ſo far were they from being appealed by his ſinful compliance, as that they grew the more furious againſt him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereby you provoke the Lord to withdraw the Covert of his Protection from you; while you <hi>wait on the Lord, and keep his Way,</hi> you have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36740:16"/> the promiſe of his Protection, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2. but if by ſinful compliance with the wicked, you forſake him, he will forſake you; you forfeit his protection: Had not <hi>Jehoſaphat's</hi> compliance with <hi>Ahab</hi> like to have coſt him his life? 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. and hear what the Prophet ſayes to him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2. <hi>Shouldſt thou help the ungodly, and love them that hate the Lord? therefore is wrath come upon thee from the Lord:</hi> And through the wrath of the Lord that is upon men for their ſinful compliance, thoſe very evils are brought upon them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, which they think to eſcape: As notable is that inſtance which Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> gives account of, on <hi>Richard Denton,</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> dayes; who by his ſinful compliance with the wicked World, in diſowning the truth of the Goſpel, thought to eſcape burning, and was afterwards burnt in his own houſe: according to that of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>He that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it,</hi> Mat. 16.25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Others think that to avenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in paying the wicked in their own Coyn, doing miſchief unto them, is the ſafeſt way; but their errour will be manifeſt from that of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.52. <hi>Put up again thy Sword into its place; for all they that take the Sword, ſhall periſh by the Sword:</hi> This way in which they think to provide for their ſafety, is in the judgement of our Saviour, the ready way to their ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Others think by Shuffling, Lying, &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocating,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36740:16"/> to provide better for their ſafety, then by keeping the <hi>Way of the Lord;</hi> but howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſome preſent ſecurity ſometimes hath been obtained by ſuch wayes, yet in the end they are moſt pernicious and deſtructive for us; Prov. 19.5. <hi>He that ſpeaketh Lyes, ſhall not eſcape:</hi> and verſ. 9. <hi>He that ſpeaketh Lyes ſhall periſh.</hi> And for ſuch as comfort themſelves, as they, Iſa. 28.25. <hi>We have made Lyes our refuge, and under Falſhood have we hid our ſelves:</hi> Mind what the Lord ſaith to them, verſ. 17. <hi>Judgement will I alſo lay to the Line, and Righteouſneſs to the Plummet; and the hail ſhall ſweep away the refuge of Lyes; and the waters ſhall overflow the hiding-place; and your Covenant with Death ſhall be diſſanulled, and your agreement with Hell ſhall not ſtand; when the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowing ſcourge ſhall paſſe through, then ſhall you be trodden down by it:</hi> and then where is your ſafety? they think to ſecure themſelves from the wrath of man; but they mind not how to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured from the wrath of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly, Others think by baſely deſerting their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to provide better for their ſafety, than by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the <hi>Lord,</hi> and keeping his <hi>Way.</hi> But the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards <hi>David</hi> was in when he took this courſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27. may convince theſe men of their miſtake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſpecially if they conſider that he that leaves the place God hath ſet him in, out of baſe fear, is ſure to carry his fear with him where-ever he go, if not (in the place he promiſed himſelf greateſt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36740:17"/> to meet with the evil he feared: As the Lord threatens them in that, <hi>Jer.</hi> 42.17. <hi>Then it ſhall come to paſſe, that the Sword which ye fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall overtake you there in the Land of Egypt; and the Famine whereof you were affraid, ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low cloſe after you in Egypt, and there ye ſhall dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Others think it a ſafer way rebelliouſly to ſtep out of their places, for the overturning the power of thoſe that are in Authority over them, becauſe they grant power to the wicked to oppreſs and miſchief them: But had <hi>Zimri</hi> peace that ſlew his Maſter? the experience of all Ages teſtifies how ill they provide for their ſafety, at the long-run, who take this courſe: Let that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſuffice which we have in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.3.</p>
            <p>So that whatever men may think, there is no ſuch way to eſcape the miſchief intended againſt us by the wicked, as to <hi>wait on the Lord, &amp; keep his Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It will yet further appear to be the ſafeſt way, for that it is the ready way to have good by all their troubles, by all that the wicked do againſt them: <hi>Wait on the Lord, and keep his Way,</hi> then no matter though the wicked watch againſt you to do you a miſchief; for they ſhall not only prove abortive in all the miſchievous deſigns they are big with, as <hi>Job</hi> 5.12. but according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, all ſhall work together for good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. for he that hath promiſed, is infinite in Power, Wiſdome, Goodneſs, and Faithfulneſs, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule all the devices and deſigns of his and your
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36740:17"/> Enemies, ſo as to make thoſe things that are in their own nature againſt you, to work together for your good: As you know what <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſays, in that <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.20. <hi>As for you, ye thought evil againſt me, but God meant it unto good, to bring to paſs, as it is this day, to ſave much people alive.</hi> Thus doth God over-rule the malice and revenge of men for good to his people; but they muſt then <hi>wait on the Lord, and keep his Way;</hi> as you may ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.8, &amp;c. <hi>For all the Paths of the Lord are Mercy and Truth unto ſuch as keep his Covenant and his Teſtimonies.</hi> When the wicked ſmite and oppreſs the people of God, they are the Lords Rod, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.5. wherewith he chaſtiſeth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And that of the Apoſtle holds in this, as well as in other chaſtiſements, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10. <hi>He for our profit, that we might be partakers of his holineſſe;</hi> as alſo what follows in <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Now no chaſtiſement for the preſent ſeemeth joyous, but grievous; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, afterward it yieldeth the peaceable fruit of Righteouſneſs to them which are exerciſed thereby,</hi> ſo as that they wait on God in the <hi>Way</hi> of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and keep the <hi>Way</hi> of his Commandments. Thus I have cleared it to be the ſafeſt <hi>Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This is the moſt honourable <hi>Way;</hi> though it were a ſafe way, yet if it be not an honourable way, it is not the beſt Way. That proved a ſafe way that <hi>David</hi> took, in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.1, 2, 3. but it was a diſhonourable way; and however, under the power of temptations he concludes it beſt,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36740:18"/> yet afterward he finds, by woful experience, his miſtake. It was a ſafe way that they adviſed <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> to, in <hi>Nehem.</hi> 6.10. but becauſe it was diſhonourable, he would not take it; <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>And he ſaid, Should ſuch a man as I fly? and who is there, being as I am, would go into the Temple to ſave his life? I will not go in:</hi> He would not ſo diſhonour his place. To run hazards in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>way,</hi> hath always been more eligible to Spirits truly noble, then ſneekingly to provide for ſafety in a baſe diſhonourable <hi>way.</hi> Now the <hi>way</hi> that is before you, is the moſt honourable <hi>way,</hi> as will appear in theſe following Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'Tis the <hi>way</hi> of true valour and courage. When the wicked watcheth to miſchieve you, when the wicked, even your Enemies and Foes come upon you to eat up your fleſh, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.2. then to <hi>wait on the Lord,</hi> to ſtand your <hi>ground,</hi> to follow <hi>the Lord,</hi> to keep his <hi>way,</hi> This is an argument of a brave and gallant Spirit. Was it not a proof of a heroick and brave Spirit in <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſays to them, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. <hi>What mean you to weep, and to break my heart? for I am ready, not to be bound only, but to dye at Jeruſalem for the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> When men are bold and daring in a wicked way, and will reſolutely keep on, whatever difficulties or oppoſition they meet with, this is not true valour, but a mad hardineſs, and deſperate ſtoutneſs of ſpirit: But when men are couragious and undaunted in following the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36740:18"/> Lord, ſtedfaſtly keeping and walking on in his Way, maugre all oppoſition that Satan and wicked Men make againſt them, this is true valour and gallantry of Spirit. Such brave and heroick Spirits were they, mentioned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35, 36, 37. who have this honourable Teſtimonial of the Lord, <hi>ver.</hi> 38. <hi>of whom the World was not worthy:</hi> Perſons, whereof every one was more worth than a world, or too excellent to abide in the world, being wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of better and greater honour than the world could give them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis the way by which you ſhall moſt victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly triumph over all your enemies: <hi>Wait on the Lord, and keep his Way,</hi> and you ſhall go on conquering and to conquer, over Sin, Satan, the World, and Antichriſt, over all your enemies; <hi>Through God you ſhall do valiantly, for he it is that ſhall tread down all your enemies,</hi> Pſal. 108.13. <hi>For this is the victory that overcometh the world, even your Faith,</hi> 1 John 5.4. Through Faith, whereby we wait on God, and keep his way, we ſhall overcome the world, that is, Satan and all his wicked crew, with all the inſtruments of miſchief they make uſe of againſt us. Hence that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. <hi>In all theſe things we are more than Conquerours, through him that loved us.</hi> And this honour have all they, that wait on the Lord, and keep his way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis the way by which you ſhall bring moſt honour to God, to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36740:19"/> of your Salvation. That the People of God are imployed in ſervice whereby God is honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that reflects honour upon them; and the more God is honoured, the more honour have they that ſerve him. The Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> counted <hi>Solomon's</hi> ſervants happy, who waited continually upon him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.8. how much more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable is it to wait on the Lord, in that a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than <hi>Solomon</hi> is here? <hi>Now wait on the Lord, and keep his way; herein you will greatly honour the Lord.</hi> As they that diſſert and forſake the Lord and his wayes, when it comes to any hard ſervice, do greatly diſhonour him; as if there were not enough to be had to make amends for all their hardſhips they endure; So they that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lord, and keep his way, through ſharp oppoſitions and ſufferings, they greatly honour him in the world. To cleave to the Lord, and follow him, when all the world are about our ears for his ſake; to keep his Way, when that his way is every where ſpoken againſt; to continue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in his Service, when nothing but bonds and perſecutions attend us for it; this commends his Service, and tendeth much to the honour of his Name and Wayes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This is the ready way to <hi>true Honour;</hi> As the wiſe man hath it in that, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.18. <hi>He that waiteth on his maſter, ſhall be honoured:</hi> So wait on the Lord, and keep his Way, and you ſhall he honoured, and that with <hi>true Honour,</hi> even that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36740:19"/> honour that is of God. In that <hi>John</hi> 5.44. our Saviour diſtinguiſheth between that Honour that is of men, and that Honour that is of God; and that is the <hi>true Honour</hi> that is of God: For as they ſay, <hi>Honor eſt in honorante, non in honorato,</hi> in him that honoureth; and then that is true and higheſt honour that is from the onely true God, that high and onely One. Now this honour have all they that waiting on the Lord, and keeping his Way, do honour him: 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Him that honoureth me, I will honour:</hi> and ſayes our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 12.26. <hi>If any man ſerve me, let him follow me; and where I am, there ſhall my ſervant be:</hi> and what honour that is, you may gather from that <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. And it further follows, <hi>If any man ſerve me, him will my Father honour.</hi> Thus it appears to be the moſt honourable way.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, This is the moſt comfortable way. It muſt be granted, 'tis a way that is attended with ſufferings, tribulations and diſtreſſes, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. and yet it is the moſt comfortable way, as will appear; In that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is the ready way to have peace, inward peace, the beſt peace in the midſt of all the trouble the world can bring upon you; In that, <hi>John</hi> 16.33. The Lord Jeſus ſaith to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that <hi>in the world they ſhould have tribulation, but in him they ſhould have peace.</hi> And to wait on the Lord, and keep his Way, is the ready way to attain this Peace, as appears from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.3.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36740:20"/> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt keep him in perfect peace whoſe mind is ſtayed on thee, becauſe he truſteth in thee.</hi> That which is rendred <hi>perfect peace,</hi> is <hi>[Peace, Peace]</hi> in the Original, the reduplication, according to the Idiome of the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> denoting the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, perfection, abundance, and duration of Peace. But to whom is this promiſe made? ſaith the Text, <hi>to him whoſe mind is ſtayed on the Lord, and truſteth in him;</hi> and in verſ. 2. <hi>to the righteous Nation which keepeth the Truth:</hi> which, according to the point in hand, may be expreſt, <hi>to them that wait on the Lord, and keep his Way.</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.165. <hi>Great Peace have they that love thy Law, and nothing ſhall offend them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis the ready way to have the Holy Ghoſt, who is ſtiled <hi>the Comforter,</hi> to abide with us. What more comfortable way, than that wherein we may be ſure to have the Comforter to be with us, to abide and continue with us? <hi>Wait on the Lord, and keep his way,</hi> ſo ſhall the Comforter abide with you for ever. Expreſſe is that of our Lord to this purpoſe, <hi>John</hi> 14.15, 16. <hi>If you love me, keep my Commandements; and I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that he may abide with you for ever.</hi> So verſ. 23. <hi>If any man love me, he will keep my words, and my Father will love him, and we will come and make our abode with him.</hi> So that this is the way to have Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, to come to us, and abide with us.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:36740:20"/>3. The Comforts which are to be had in this way, are true, ſolid, ſubſtantial and abiding Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, ſuch as fill the ſoul with inward joy and mirth, under the ſoreſt outward trouble, ſo as that they can ſing in priſon, and leap in the flames. Notable is that expreſſion of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. <hi>I am filled with comfort, I am exceeding joyful in all our tribulations in following the Lord.</hi> He tells us in the next verſe, <hi>that his fleſh had no reſt, that he was troubled on every ſide, and yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding joyful:</hi> yea, he tells us in another place, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. <hi>that as his afflictions did abound for Chriſt, ſo his conſolations did abound by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This is the way to arrive ſpeedily where the wicked ſhall trouble you no more; where there ſhall be no more ſorrow nor weeping, but where you ſhall have perfect reſt and peace, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of joy and comfort for evermore. That of the Lord Jeſus to his Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.28, 29. is plain for this, <hi>Ye are they which have continued with me in my temptations, and I appoint you a Kingdom, as my Father hath appointed unto me:</hi> with <hi>John</hi> 10.27, 28. <hi>My Sheep hear my voyce, and I know them, and they follow me, and I give unto them eternal life, and they ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall, any man pluck them out of my hand.</hi> As <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> waited on the Lord and kept his way, following him fully, and ſo entred <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and had a peaceable and comfortable poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 14.14. ſo they that wait on the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36740:21"/> Lord and keep his Way, ſhall have abundant en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into that heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. where there is fulneſs of joy, and pleaſures for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. And thus it appears to be the moſt comfortable way. To conclude: this we ſay, <hi>All is well that ends well.</hi> Now, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37. <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright; for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then we have cleared, That however it go with the People of God here in this world, more eſpecially when the wicked watch them to doe them a miſchief, 'tis their beſt way to wait on the Lord, and keep his way; for that it is the honeſteſt, the wiſeſt, the ſafeſt, and the moſt honourable and moſt comfortable way. And though I doubt not but enough hath been ſpoken to perſwade and prevail with thoſe that have an underſtanding to diſcern, and a heart to perceive what hath been ſet before them: Yet I queſtion not, but carnal reaſon hath many things to object, and ſuch as may prevail with carnal hearts to disbelieve all that hath been ſpoken, ſo far at leaſt as to prefer the wayes of carnal wiſdom, before this Way of the Lord: But I reſt ſatisfied with that anſwer of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.11. <hi>It is given to you to know the Myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven, but unto them it is not given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have the Doctrinal part of the point: I proceed to the Application: and we ſhall make uſe of this,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:36740:21"/>1. To admoniſh and forewarn all the followers of Chriſt, that have own'd, engag'd, and walk'd in the way of the Lord, to take heed that they be not ſtumbled, moved, and turned out of the way of the Lord. The Apoſtle in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.13. adviſeth them to <hi>make ſtraight paths for their feet, leſt that which is lame ſhould be turned out of the way, but let it rather be healed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is ſome lameneſs remaining with the Beſt; with ſome more, with ſome leſs; but with all ſome: It lies therefore in all to take heed leſt they be turned out of the way: Hence that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall:</hi> and let him that thinketh he is ſtabliſhed and ſetled in the way of the Lord, take heed leſt he be offended and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the way: O that a holy Jealouſie in this thing may poſſeſſe and fill all your hearts.</p>
            <p>More particularly, I would forewarn you to take heed, leſt you be offended, through ſome things, and by ſome perſons, in this day of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take heed leſt you be offended at the Croſſe: Our Saviour in the Parable of the Sower, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. tells us of ſome, who though they hear and receive the Word for a ſeaſon with joy, yet when Tribulation or Perſecution ariſeth for the Word, by and by they are offended. How is this fulfilled in our dayes! how many are there, who while the <hi>Way of the Lord</hi> was <hi>the Way to prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:36740:22"/> did profeſſe and walk in it; who now that it is oppoſed and every-where ſpoken againſt, do decline and forſake it? Be you admoniſhed to take heed, leſt the ſtumbling-block of others ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, eſpecially of faithfull Miniſters, do turn you out of the way: The Apoſtle laboureth much in removing this ſtumbling-block, as you may ſee, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.3. Therefore I do the more earneſtly forewarn you of this; and take heed leſt what ſufferings come on you for the Goſpel ſake, do turn you out of the way: you are no Diſciples for Chriſt, unleſſe you take up your Croſſe and follow him, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Take heed leſt you be offended by the falls and Apoſtacies of hypocritical profeſſors: This is that Satan and his inſtruments will lay before you to turn you out of the way of the Lord; our Saviour doth therefore forewarn of this, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. ſo likewiſe his Apoſtles, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Take heed that you be not ſtumbled by the ſcorn, contempt, and reproach that is caſt on the way of the Lord, and thoſe that walk in it. This is that Satan and his inſtruments will lay before you; That the way of the Lord and his followers are every where under reproach and contempt: for as they ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo hath the falſe Church ſaid to thoſe that teach the way of the Lord truly, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.22. <hi>For as concerning this Sect we know that every where it is ſpoken againſt;</hi> the Original is,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36740:22"/> 
               <hi>Hereſie:</hi> the way of the Lord is commonly thus branded in the world; and they that walk in it are counted a company of <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Hereticks.</hi> But this ſhould ſtumble us no more than it did <hi>Paul,</hi> who there (ver. 23.) boldly teacheth this way, and (<hi>Act.</hi> 24.14.) freely profeſſeth it. <hi>But this I confeſs to thee, that after the way which they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Take heed you be not offended at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of the wicked, eſpecially when he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wicked devices to paſs: This was that had almoſt turn'd the Pſalmiſt out of the way, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.2, 3. <hi>As for me my feet were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well-nigh ſlipt; for I was envious at the fooliſh, when I ſaw the proſperity of the wicked.</hi> To ſee thoſe that deſpiſe, hate, and perſecute the VVay of the Lord, and thoſe that walk in it, to proſper and flouriſh; while thoſe that love it, own it, and walk in it, are in an afflicted and ſuffering condition; this not only overturns formal Profeſſors, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a time puts ſincere Believers to a ſtand. Hence that advice in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.7. <hi>Fret not thy ſelf becauſe of him who proſpereth, becauſe of the man who bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wicked devices to paſs:</hi> And as ver. 8. <hi>Fret not thy ſelf in any wiſe to do evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Take heed of ſuch perſons, as by whom, if you be not the more watchful, you may be ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as to be turned out of the way. More par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:36740:23"/>1. <hi>Take heed of your ſelves.</hi> This is that our Saviour calls for, in that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. <hi>If any man will come after me, let him deny himſelf.</hi> Our greateſt danger is from our ſelves, while we have within a deceiver and a traytor, who is ſtill conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to turn us out of the way. Take heed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of your own ſelves, conſult not with fleſh and blood, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Beware of Satan.</hi> This is that which the Apoſtle ſuggeſts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>I fear by any means leaſt as the Serpent beguiled</hi> Eve <hi>through his ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity that is in Chriſt.</hi> And out of the like fear concerning you, I beſeech you beware of Satan; and the rather, for that, as the Apoſtle ſaith, verſ. 14. <hi>Satan is transformed into an Angel of light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Beware of falſe Teachers.</hi> This is the advice of our Saviour, in <hi>Math.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets, which come unto you in ſheeps cloathing, &amp;c.</hi> And though I cannot ſay, <hi>I know,</hi> with the Apoſtle in <hi>Act.</hi> 20.29. yet I am greatly afraid, <hi>that after my departing ſhall grievous Wolves enter in among you, not ſparing the Flock; and that of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Beware of worldly Friends,</hi> ſuch as will coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel you to ſpare your ſelves, ſuch as ſavour not the things of God, but thoſe that be of men. This our Saviour calls for in that of <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. Anſwer them as Chriſt anſwered <hi>Peter,</hi> Mat. 16.22, 23.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:36740:23"/>
            <p>The proper uſe of this Point, with reſpect to the people of God, is, To exhort and perſwade them, <hi>to wait on the Lord, and keep his way,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, whoever they are that watch and plot againſt them, however they may proſper in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wicked devices to paſs; however, they may prevail in oppreſſing the poor Saints, yet this is the exhortation that I have received from the Lord for you, <hi>Wait on the Lord, and keep his Way.</hi> There are two branches of the Exhortation, I ſhall ſpeak to both of them diſtinctly.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the latter of them is the main, and the former a help thereto in bad times; I ſhall invert the order of the Text, and ſpeak to what is here, the latter in the firſt place, and to the other as time will give leave.</p>
            <p n="1">1. However it go, Saints, though the wicked watch to do you a miſchief, yet keep you the Way of the Lord, diligently obſerving the way of his Commandments, the way of your duty to walk therein. Foraſmuch as it hath been the deſign of my preaching all-along, to expound the Way of God to you, and to inſtruct you in the Way of the Lord; And I am now directing my Speech to the Saints of God, who know, own, and profeſs the Way of the Lord. I ſhall not ſpend much time (while I have ſo little left) in recounting to you what I have taught you concerning the way of the Lord, only in general, that Way of Truth and Righteouſneſs, the Way of Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36740:24"/> which I have taught you from the VVord, is intended. You know the way of Goſpel-Doctrin, Goſpel-Fellowſhip, Goſpel-VVorſhip, Goſpel-Diſcipline, and Goſpel-Converſation, which I have preached, and you have received. And here Beloved, I call God to witneſs, in whoſe Name I have preached to you, that I have preached the VVay of the Lord ſincerely and faithfully, as I have received of the Lord by the teaching of his Spirit through the VVord; I therefore beſeech and entreat you, out of that hearty love I bear to you, and that affectionate care I have for you, that as you tender the Glory of God, your own Peace here, and eternal Happineſs hereafter, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and eternal Good of others, that you will remember how you have heard, and received, and keep the VVay of the Lord.</p>
            <p>In the proſecuting of this, I ſhall ſpeak to theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Open this duty in a few particulars.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Give you ſome Directions to help you herein.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, take it in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be exhorted to keep the VVay of the Lord in your memories: So <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Remember there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how thou haſt received, and heard, and hold faſt.</hi> I am ſpeaking to thoſe that have received the knowledge of the VVay of the Lord, that they retain what they have learned, and that they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an actual remembrance of it: and the rather
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36740:24"/> take heed to this, every one of you, with the greater diligence, for that you are like to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the help of your Remembrancers, <hi>viz.</hi> the faithful Miniſters of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. you have had their help a long while, in putting you, from Sabbath to Sabbath, in remembrance; but this is taking from you: as the Apoſtle in another caſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Therefore ye ought to give the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt heed to the things ye have heard, leaſt at any time ye ſhould let them ſlip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Keep the VVay of the Lord in your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Conſciences: I am ſpeaking to thoſe whoſe Judgments are enlightned, and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces renewed, to approve of the VVay of the Lord: As therefore the Apoſtle ſaid unto them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Ye therefore, Beloved, ſeeing ye know theſe things before, beware, leaſt ye alſo be led away with the errour of the wicked, and fall from your own ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs.</hi> So ſay I, ſeeing ye know the VVay of the Lord, and approve of it, beware, leſt being led away with the errour of the wicked, and your own Judgments being thereby corrupted, and your Conſciences defiled, you fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſſe: And I the rather preſs this, for that as the Apoſtle hath it, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. <hi>I fear leſt by any means, as the Serpent beguiled Eve through his ſubtilty, ſo your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Keep the VVay of the Lord in your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: I am ſpeaking unto thoſe, who, as <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:36740:25"/> 10.10. with the <hi>heart, believe unto righteouſneſs;</hi> and with the <hi>mouth, make confeſſion unto ſalvation:</hi> And you have the Exhortation in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. <hi>Let us hold faſt the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Faith, without wavering:</hi> Be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of your Profeſſion; as our Saviour ſpeaks, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.38. <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my Words, in this adulterous and ſinful Generation, of him alſo ſhall the Son of man be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when he cometh in the Glory of his Father, with his holy Angels;</hi> with Mat. 10.32, 33. <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall confeſs me before men, him will I confeſs alſo before my Father which is in Heaven: But whoſoever ſhall deny me before men, him will I alſo deny before my Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Keep the VVay of the Lord in your <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>affections,</hi> loving, rejoycing, and delighting in the VVay of the Lord: The keeping of it in your Memories, Judgments and Profeſſion, will be but in vain, unleſs you keep it in your hearts. Lay up and hide the VVord of God in your hearts; let the deſire and delight of your Soul be in the VVay of the Lord, with the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.111. <hi>Thy Teſtimonies have I taken for mine heritage for ever; for they are the rejoycing of my heart:</hi> 'Tis the Character of the Godly man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>He delighteth in the Law of the Lord; and in his Law doth he meditate day and night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Keep the Way of the Lord in your <hi>lives</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36740:25"/> 
               <hi>converſations;</hi> walking therein conſcientiouſly; obſerving the Commandments of God to do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: I am ſpeaking to thoſe who have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the way of the Lord to walk in; and they may read what the Lord ſaith in that, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.32. <hi>You ſhall obſerve to do as the Lord your God hath commanded you: You ſhall not turn aſide to the right hand, or to the left: you ſhall walk in all the Wayes that the Lord your God hath commanded you: And to as many as walk according to this Rule, peace ſhall be upon them, and upon the Iſrael of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus opened this Duty, take theſe few Directions among the many that might be given.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let the Spirit of Chriſt be your guide and principle: I am ſpeaking unto ſuch as have the Spirit of Chriſt: Now if you conſult that, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. you ſhall find that the Lord promiſeth his People, that he will put his Spirit within them: and to what purpoſe? <hi>viz.</hi> both to encline, enable, and guide them to walk in his Statutes, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his Commandments to do them. There is no entring into the VVay of the Lord, but by the Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3. we all naturally being gone aſtray, wander from the way of the Lord, and 'tis the Spirit only that can, and doth reduce men into this way; and the beſt being but lame, and having not only a principle of halting in, but declining from it, there is no walking in this VVay, but by the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36740:26"/> aſſiſtance and guidance of the Spirit. Let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Spirit of God be your guide; it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, that he ſhall <hi>lead you into all Truth,</hi> John 16.13. Let the Spirit be your principle: <hi>walk in the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 5.16. <hi>then you ſhall not fulfil the luſts of the fleſh;</hi> but ſhall keep the Way of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Make the Word of God your Rule. I have heretofore, from that <hi>John</hi> 6.39. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. and ſeveral other places, cleared to you, that it is given of God for this end, to be the Rule both for Faith and Practice. Keep there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unto this, and by no means depart from this, if you would keep the VVay of the Lord. Here you have the Lord revealing his Way, and that clearly and plainly, ſo that the moſt ſimple, that apply themſelves to it, may underſtand it: the Scriptures are a perfect and a conſtant Rule: Therefore, as in that <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony; if they ſpeak not according to this Word, 'tis becauſe there is no Light in them.</hi> There are ſome that make the <hi>Light within,</hi> their Rule, and that in oppoſition to the VVord: but the Light in ſuch is <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> for if they ſpeak not according to this VVord (if it be but diverſe from, though not directly oppoſite unto it) then there is no light in them. Indeed the <hi>Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> that is, Conſcience enlightned, is a Rule; but it is <hi>Regula Regulata,</hi> a Ruled Rule: There is <hi>Regula Regulans,</hi> and <hi>Regula Regulata,</hi> A Ruling
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:36740:26"/> Rule, and a Ruled Rule: The former is a Rule to the latter, by which it is to be tryed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved: The Word of God is a ruling Rule; and Conſcience is a ruled Rule, which is to be obeyed, as far as it ſpeaks according to the Word, and no further. If therefore you would keep the Way of the Lord, do not deſpiſe Conſcience; do not neglect the Light within; but make it not thy Rule: make the VVord of God thy Rule; admit not of any thing that is belonging to the VVay of the Lord, that is not grounded upon, or not warranted by his Word. If you would keep the Way of the Lord, hold faſt to what is written, ſtick to the Word.</p>
            <p>That ſaying of <hi>Auſtin</hi> is famous;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sive de Chriſto, ſive de Eccleſia, ſive de quacun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que alia re non dico ſi nos ſed ſi Angelus de caelo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis annunciaverit praeterquam quod in Scripturis accipiſtes, Anathema ſit:</hi> Not to ſay, If we, but if an Angel from Heaven ſhall preach any thing of Chriſt, or of the Church, or of any other thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what ye have received in the Scriptures, let him be accurſed: Like to that, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. The Word is the heavenly compaſs whereby we may be directed to ſteer our courſe aright to the Haven of happineſs: Keep you to the Word, while one ſays, this is the way, and another that: Try all things by the Rule of the Word, and make that your Rule to walk by. Hence, when <hi>Paul</hi> was taking his leave of the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36740:27"/> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> 20. In his <hi>Farewel-Sermon,</hi> that after his departure, they might <hi>keep the Way of the Lord:</hi> you may read, what he commends to them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. <hi>And now Brethren, I commend you to God, and the Word of his Grace, which is able to build you up, and give you an Inheritance among thoſe that are ſanctified:</hi> He recommends the Word of God to them. So, Beloved, now that I may no more ſpeak to you from this place, for the teaching of you the <hi>right</hi> and the <hi>good</hi> Way, I recommend to you the Word of the Lord; which will be a Light to your feet, and a Lanthorn to your Paths, to guide you in the Way of the Lord, till you attain the end of your Faith, the Salvation of your Souls. What knowledge I have of the Way of the Lord, what I have taught you of the VVay of the Lord, I have been taught by the Spirit of the Lord, through the VVord: and though you want the great help of a plain, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and faithful Miniſtry, for the future, yet let not thoſe that are ſincere, in deſiring to walk in the VVay of the Lord, be diſcouraged by thoſe who would make them believe, that the VVord is hard to be underſtood: for that, as it is more from malignity in us, than difficulty in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that the moſt do not underſtand them; ſo they are eaſie to be underſtood by them that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely endeavour: it being not only moſt plain and clear in teaching the Way of the Lord, but alſo appointed to enlighten the eyes, and make
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36740:27"/> wiſe the ſimple, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7, 8. Yea, the entrance of it giveth Light: it giveth underſtanding to the ſimple, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.130. And how weak and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſoever any of the Saints may be in worldly matters, and in the VVorlds account, yet of them all is that ſpoken, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.27. <hi>But the Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which ye have received of Him, abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth, and is no lye; and even as it hath taught you, ye ſhall abide in Him.</hi> Though they corrupt and pervert this Text, that make uſe of it to the diſanulling of all Miniſterial teaching; for if <hi>John</hi> had meant ſo, to what purpoſe did he write this Epiſtle? yet when God depriveth us of this help, this Scripture affords ſupport and comfort to the Saints, that by the Spirit in them, they ſhall be enabled to underſtand what he teacheth in the Word, ſo as to abide in the Lord and in his Way, as they have been taught.</p>
            <p>Having then the Spirit for your principle and guide, let the VVord be your Rule, and you ſhall keep the VVay of the Lord; according to that promiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8. <hi>The way faring-men, though fools, ſhall not err therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let the example of Chriſt be your pattern, that you may keep the Way of the Lord; ſet this copy alwayes before you. He alwayes kept the Way of the Lord: as he came down from Heaven to do the VVill of his Father, <hi>John</hi> 6.38. ſo he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36740:28"/> did alwayes thoſe things that did pleaſe him, <hi>John</hi> 8.29. He never departed in the leaſt from the VVay of the Lord: <hi>He knew no ſin, neither was guile found in his mouth.</hi> If then you would keep the VVay of the Lord, learn of him, follow him, walk even as he walked: Indeed in the things that are proper to Chriſt, as God, or as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, therein he is not to be imitated by us; but in the things that he did, or ſuffered as man, he left us an example or pattern, that we ſhould follow his ſteps, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. Hence that exhortation of his, Mat. 11.29. <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart.</hi> That then you may be directed as well as encouraged to keep the VVay of the Lord; look to Jeſus, and walk as you have him for an example. Indeed the Apoſtle exhorts to walk, as you have Him for an example, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. But knowing that he could give them but an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect copy, he exhorts in that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Be ye followers of me, even as I alſo am of Chriſt:</hi> It may be of good uſe to us, to mind the Examples of the Apoſtles and faithful Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, that have walkt on in the VVay of the Lord before us: But foraſmuch as there is none of them, even <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, but went awry more or leſs: Therefore make the example of Chriſt your pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern. Time will not permit to proſecute this at large: I ſhall only offer ſome few particulars from the example of Chriſt to you, ſuch as may be moſt ſeaſonable to further you in keeping the VVay of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:36740:28"/>1. It was the work and buſineſs of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to do the VVill of his Father, to do what pleaſed him. As he came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to do his Fathers VVill, as you before heard from <hi>John</hi> 6.68. ſo he made it his work and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. To this purpoſe is that, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.49. <hi>How is it that ye ſought me? wiſt ye not that I muſt be about my Fathers buſineſs?</hi> with that <hi>John</hi> 4.34. <hi>Jeſus ſaith unto them, My meat is to do the Will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work.</hi> If then you will keep the VVay of the Lord herein, be ye followers of Chriſt; let it be your work and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to do the VVill of the Lord, and to walk in all well-pleaſing before him: Let the Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be in the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Furthermore, then we beſeech you Brethren, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you, That as you have received of us how you ought to walk and to pleaſe God, ſo ye would abound more and more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It was the practice of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to look on all the ſufferings that came upon him, as coming from the hand of his Father in accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of his Word, and therefore quietly to ſubmit to them. To this purpoſe is it that he tells <hi>Pilate</hi> in <hi>John</hi> 19.11. <hi>Thou couldſt have no power at all againſt me, except it were given thee from above;</hi> He looks beyond <hi>Pilate</hi> to him that was above. So <hi>John</hi> 18.11. <hi>The Cup which my Father hath given me, ſhall I not drink it?</hi> He over looks the inſtruments, and looks on his ſufferings, as a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36740:29"/> cup put into his hand by his Father: And as he obſerved the hand of his Father in the ſufferings that came upon him, ſo he takes notice that they are in accompliſhment of Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.53, 54. <hi>Thinkeſt thou that I could not now pray to my Father; and he ſhall preſently give me more than twelve legions of Angels? but how then ſhall the Scriptures be fulfilled, that thus it muſt be?</hi> and he takes notice that the Scriprure had foretold that <hi>thus it muſt be,</hi> and that <hi>he muſt ſuffer, and enter into glory,</hi> as he clears it in that of <hi>Luke</hi> 24.25, 26. Therefore though he prayed, <hi>if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> as <hi>Mathew</hi> hath it; and, <hi>if thou be willing, let this Cup paſs from me,</hi> as <hi>Luke</hi> hath it; yet he quietly ſubmits to his Fathers VVill, with a, <hi>Not my will, but thine be done.</hi> And as <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.42. <hi>If this cup may not paſs away, except I drink it, let thy will be done.</hi> Thus you ſee how by looking to the Fathers hand, he willingly ſubmits to what ſufferings came upon him. That you may keep the Way of the Lord in the midſt of all the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings you are like to meet with, herein following the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, eying the hand of your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Father in all the ſufferings that come upon you, of what nature ſoever, and by whomſoever inflicted; and whatever may be the ends of thoſe by whom you ſuffer, yet that they are all ordered by him in accompliſhment of his VVord. Do ye not believe this? I know that ye do believe it by Faith; therefore improve it for the quieting of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36740:29"/> your hearts in all your ſufferings. This is that the Apoſtle preſſeth the Saints unto in the 12th of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> where he taketh for granted, that all kind of ſufferings, (more eſpecially ſuch as come upon us by the contradiction of ſinners) are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly corrections from the Lord, and ſo in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of the VVord of God, according unto that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.30, 31. and therefore hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to be ſubmitted to: ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9, 10. <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, we have had fathers of our fleſh which corrected us, and we gave them reverence: ſhall we not much rather be in ſubjection to the Father of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and live? for they verily for a few dayes cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened us after their own pleaſure; but he for our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, that we may be partakers of his Holineſs.</hi> Seeing therefore whatſoever befalls you in the Way of the Lord, is by your Father's ordering in accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of his VVord for your profit, that ye may be partakers of his Holineſs: ſubmit your ſelves to him, eye your Fathers hand and end, and be quiet.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was the practice of Jeſus Chriſt in his ſtate of humiliation, to give unto Civil Magiſtrates and Rulers what was their due, yea to forgo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of his Civil Right rather than to offend them: For giving unto Civil Magiſtrates their due, notable is that of <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Render therefore unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and unto God the things that are God's.</hi> And as he taught them, ſo he practiſed himſelf; for he was not of thoſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:36740:30"/> who ſay and do not, but his practice was alwayes conformable to his Doctrine: VVhen therefore they that received Tribute-money at <hi>Capernaum,</hi> came and demanded of him; he will rather recede from his Civil Liberty than offend them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.25, 26, 27. Now go ye and do likewiſe. If ye will keep the VVay of the Lord, give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars,</hi> be ſubject unto the King and all that are in Authority: Let the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation be that, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.</hi> VVhat is here meant by Ordinance of man, is clear from what follows, <hi>whether to the King as ſupream, or unto Governors, &amp;c.</hi> Be ye therefore ſubject, Saints, not only for wrath, but for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, for the Lord's ſake; and as <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Render to every one their due; Tribute to whom Tribute, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom is due, &amp;c.</hi> Such ſubjection to Magiſtrates as thwarteth not our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience unto God, lies within the Way of the Lord: Yeeld therefore active obedience unto the King, as far as Conſcience towards God will give leave: <hi>Fear God and honour the King,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.17. Give all that honour to the King that is conſiſtent with the true Fear of God. Let nothing but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God hinder you at any time from yeelding active obedience to all the King's Laws.</p>
            <p>And here Beloved, I ſhall take occaſion to open my heart ſincerely to you. You know what
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36740:30"/> is required of me if I will continue a publick Miniſter in this Kingdom: I hope no ſober perſons can think me ſuch a humerous perverſe <hi>Phanatick</hi> as to throw away my Maintenance, much leſſe my Miniſterial Capacity (which is much more dear to me than Livelihood, yea than Life) out of a proud humor and vain-glorious fancy. In brief therefore, as I ſhall anſwer it before the great God the ſearcher of all hearts, and the righteous Judge, did not Conſcience towards God forbid me, I would willingly and readily do all that the Act requires. But ſeeing I cannot declare an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Aſſent and Conſent, as the Law requires: As from the fear of my God I dare not; ſo from the love you generally have to me, I know you would not have me diſſemble with God and men. I do therefore humbly chooſe to ſubmit to the Penalty, rather than by a hypocritical conformity (for ſuch it muſt be in me, if any) to diſhonour my God, wound my own Conſcience, and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with men; knowing aſſuredly that my God hath no need of my ſin; And if he have any work for me in the publick Miniſtry, he will encline the King's heart to grant Liberty and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein to me, with the reſt of thoſe who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be faithful in preaching of the Goſpel; which that the Lord will grant, I promiſe my ſelf the help of all your prayers, who have been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured with any ſpiritual bleſſings through my Miniſtry.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:36740:31"/>4. It was the practice of Jeſus Chriſt to be ſo far from making reſiſtance by the ſword to keep himſelf from ſuffering, that he refuſed ſuch help as was offered him that way: So <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.52. <hi>Then ſaid Jeſus unto him, Put up again thy ſword into his place; for all they that take the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; 'tis not all that uſe, but all that take the ſword without a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful call. So <hi>John</hi> 18.11. <hi>Put up thy ſword into thy ſheath: the Cup which my Father will have me to drink, ſhall I not drink it?</hi> If you would keep the Way of the Lord herein, follow Chriſt ſo, as not to reſiſt thoſe that are in Authority, however unjuſtly you may ſuffer from them: for, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. <hi>This is thank-worthy, if a man for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence-ſake toward God endure grief, ſuffering wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It was the practice of Jeſus Chriſt to be ſo far from avenging himſelf, as to render good for evil, to forgive his enemies, to ſeek their good and welfare. So in <hi>Luke</hi> 23.34. <hi>Then ſaid Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus follow Chriſt, according to that he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Love your enemies; Bleſſe them that curſe you; do good to them that hate you; and pray for them which deſpitefully uſe you, and perſecute you.</hi> And what the Apoſtle exhorteth in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19, 20. <hi>Dearly beloved, avenge not your ſelves, but rather give place unto wrath: for it is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:36740:31"/> written, Vengeance is mine, I will repay, ſaith the Lord. Therefore if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirſt, give him drink, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt had great compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for poor wandering ſinners, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.36. Great love for his Saints, <hi>John</hi> 13.1. with tender pity towards them in all their ſorrows and afflictions, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. Herein alſo be ye followers of Chriſt, according to that, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>Put on therefore as the Elect of God, holy and beloved, bowels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, kindneſs, humbleneſſe of mind, meekneſſe, long-ſuffering, forbearing one another, and forgiving one another; if any man have a quarrel againſt any, even as Chriſt forgave you, ſo alſo do ye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The Lord Jeſus counted not his life dear, when that he was called to give it up in bearing witneſſe to the Truth; as you have it in that <hi>John</hi> 18.37. he bears witneſſe to the Truth when cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to it, with the hazard of his life.</p>
            <p>Herein follow Jeſus Chriſt, in bearing Witneſs to the Truth of God, though with the hazard of your lives, as <hi>Paul</hi> doth in that, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24. Whatever miſchief be threatned by wicked men, yet deny not, be not aſhamed of the Words, Truths, and Wayes of Chriſt; for 'tis the Word of the true and faithful Witneſs, which we have <hi>Mark</hi> 8.36. <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall be aſhamed of me and my words, in this adulterous and ſinful Generation, of him alſo ſhall the Son of man be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when he cometh in the glory of his Father, with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:36740:32"/> the holy Angels.</hi> And, Oh how ſad, if this be thy portion! for if in that day Chriſt ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thee, Wo be to thee for ever, thou ſhalt be wretched and miſerable to all Eternity. But be faithful, couragious, and conſtant, in confeſſing him, and his Wayes and Truths; for he hath ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe me before men, him will I confeſſe before my Father that is in Heaven:</hi> And, Oh how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, if this be thy Portion! for if Jeſus Chriſt confeſſe thee at that day, Peace be to thee for ever, thou ſhalt be bleſſed and happy to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: Though therefore thy confeſſing of him, be attended not only with Reproaches, and Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, but with Fines, Bonds, Impriſonment, yea Death it ſelf; yet herein follow him, in bearing witneſs to the Truth, when called unto it, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hazard you run by it; yea though it come to the drinking of the Cup that he drank of, and to the ſealing of your Teſtimony with your blood; <hi>knowing that if ye ſuffer with him, you ſhall alſo reign together with him.</hi> Thus if you follow the Lord, walking in his ſteps, in theſe and other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, wherein he hath given us an example, you ſhall be ſure to keep the Way of the Lord. And this ſhall ſuffice for the third branch of the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let the Glory of God be your End, if that you would keep the way of the Lord. If you have ſincerely entred the Way of the Lord, then
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:36740:32"/> the Glory of the Lord is your laſt End; and if you would keep on ſteadily in this way, look to the Glory of God as your main End. Though it be poſſible for a man that hath the Glory of God for his End, to ſtep out of the Way of the Lord; yet it is impoſſible for a man to keep the Way of the Lord, unleſs this be his utmoſt End: Yea though it be poſſible for one that is right in his End, to err in this or that particular, ſo as to ſtray from the Way of the Lord, in ſome leſſer matters that ſhall not prejudice his Salvation; yet it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that ſuch a one ſhould ſo miſtake about the Subſtantials of this Way, as to turn aſide, and to walk totally and finally in the Way that leadeth to deſtruction, and eternal perdition: Though the purity of the End, will not make amends for the viciouſneſs of the means; yet where a man is right in his End, much Errour as to the means ſhall be forgiven him; yea and to have the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God for your End, in all your natural and civil Actions, is the way to ſanctifie them, and to inſcribe <hi>Holineſs to the Lord</hi> on them. Thus may the meaneſt actions of your particular Callings become Religious, if they be done as to the Lord in obedience to his Command, and with reſpect to his Glory: Therefore as the Apoſtle hath it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Whether you eat or drink, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ye do, do all to the Glory of God:</hi> Make this your ſcope, and it will be of ſpecial uſe to guide you when the way is doubtful, being indeed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36740:33"/> by the Apoſtle for that end: As a man that is travelling on <hi>Salisbury Plain</hi> towards the City; he comes ſomtimes where there is no bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten paths, and ſomtimes where two or three ways meet; now to keep his eye on the City, is the ready courſe to keep him in the right way: So if a man were to draw a ſtreight Line to ſuch a Point, and hath not a Rule to draw by, his readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt way is to keep his eye upon the Point. So when your way is doubtful, and you know not which way to take, take that which is moſt for the Glory of God: where you ſee not your Rule, keep your eye on the Glory of God, and it will be of choice uſe to keep you ſtreight in the Way of the Lord. And ſo much for the firſt branch of the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be exhorted to wait on the Lord, for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this you will not long keep the VVay of the Lord; there are ſuch troubles, diſtreſſes and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations that attend the Way of the Lord, that as the Apoſtle hath it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36. <hi>Ye have need of Patience, that after ye have done the will of God, you may inherit the Promiſe.</hi> So ſay I, you have need of waiting, that you may keep the Way of the Lord, and continue therein to the end.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Nature of this Duty lies, and what Encouragements there are to it in the worſt of times, I have lately ſhewn you, when I preached on that, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.26. <hi>It is good that a man hope,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36740:33"/> and wait quietly for the Salvation of the Lord.</hi> Whence I obſerved, That however it go with the people of God, it is good, it is beſt for them to hope, and wait quietly for the Salvation of the Lord. I ſhall therefore only recommend this Duty to you, as the work of this dark Day, and conclude with that of our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.35, &amp;c. <hi>And let your Loyns be girded about, and your Lights burning, and ye your ſelves like to men that wait for their Lord when he will return from the Wedding; that when he cometh and knocketh, they may open to him immediately. Bleſſed are thoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whom the Lord when he cometh ſhall find watching.</hi> Yea, <hi>Keep the Way of the Lord, and wait on him:</hi> For, as verſ. 42, 43. <hi>Who then is that faithful and wiſe Steward, whom his Lord ſhall make Ruler over his Houſhold, to give them their Portion of meat in due ſeaſon. Bleſſed is that Servant, whom the Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:36740:34"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36740:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
